## EHEDI HASAN

Scholar ORCID

#### RESEARCH INTEREST

I am a Software Engineer specializing in Algorithms & Research at Chaldal. Outside of work, I am involved in academic research. My primary area of interest is Human Computer Interaction, including Accessibility, Security & Privacy, Health & Eudaimonia. I'm also passionate about Visualization, VR/AR, and Ubiquitous technologies. Through my work experience, I've gained expertise and interest in Algorithms and Systems, including Networking, Distributed Systems and System Design.

#### **EDUCATION**

### **BSc** in Computer Science and Engineering

May 2023

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET), Dhaka, Bangladesh

CGPA: 3.57/4.00 Last Two Terms: 3.82/4.00

Notable Courses:

CSE 305 - Computer Architecture CSE 309 - Compiler

CSE 321 - Computer Networks CSE 463 - Introduction to Bioinformatics

CSE 471 - Machine Learning CSE 409 - Computer Graphics CSE 461 - Algorithm Engineering MATH 247 - Linear Algebra

CSE 313 - Operating System MATH 145 - Calculus and Coordinate Geometry CSE 405 - Computer Security HUM 477 - Sociology for Science and Technology

## **ENGLISH PROFICIENCY**

TOEFL iBT December, 2023

Reading: 25/30, Listening: 28/30, Speaking: 30/30, Writing: 29/30 Total: 112/120

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- Mubassira, T., Hasan, M., Sharmin, S. (2024). "Reading the Mind's Eye: Detecting Trauma-Vulnerability in Individuals by Analyzing Attention Through Eye-Tracking". In: Zaslavsky, A., Ning, Z., Kalogeraki, V., Georgakopoulos, D., Chrysanthis, P.K. (eds) Mobile and Ubiquitous Systems: Computing, Networking and Services. MobiQuitous 2023 (EAI Mobiguitous 2023). DOI: 10.1007/978-3-031-63992-0\_28
- Mubassira, T., Hasan, M., Noor, J., Islam, A (2024). "Enhancing EmoBot: An In-Depth Analysis of User Expectation and Satisfaction in An Emotion-Aware Chatbot". In: International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security, 2024. DOI: 10.1145/3704522.3704527

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Detecting Sentiment in Anonymous Submissions: A Study on User Report Data

Human Computer Analysis, Sentiment Analysis

Sep 2024 - Current

- Supervisor: Dr. A. B. M. Alim Al Islam, Professor, CSE, BUET
- Contribution: Performed sentiment analysis on crowd sourced anonymous reports

### Towards perceiving and resolving the impediments to reporting for the developing countries

Human Computer Interaction, Generic Reporting System

Aug 2024 - Current

- DOI: 10.1109/NSYSS2.2017.8267790
- Live At: ureporter.cse.buet.ac.bd
- Supervisor: Dr. A. B. M. Alim Al Islam, Professor, CSE, BUET
- Collaboration: With Tarik Reza Toha, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
- **Contribution:** Improved the system in collaboration with the research team

## Fine-Tuning GPT-2 for Bengali Auto Text Completion Using Literary Corpus: A Qualitative Analysis

Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning

Jan 2023 - Mar 2023

- Presentation: Slides
- Supervisor: Dr. Mohammed Eunus Ali, Professor, CSE, BUET
- Contribution: Fine-tuned GPT-2 with a Bengali literature corpus to improve auto text completion

Chaldal Ltd. June 2023 – Present

R&D

#### **ASAP Delivery**

- Designed an algorithm to **calculate geographical area overlapping a route**, through which a driver can detour for a specific slack time period to deliver to a new location without impacting other deliveries in the route

- Impact: Grocery delivery within 20 to 40 minutes in Dhaka

## Last Mile Routing Algorithm

- Designed a new routing algorithm using different heuristic and probabilistic search methods
- Impact: Increased on-time delivery by 15%

#### Traffic Estimate

- Developed a timeseries database and supervised an interpolation project using spatio-temporal models to fill missing traffic speed data.
- Impact: Improved estimates for Dhaka roads by 53.53% for cycles, 28.83% for motorbikes, and 28.73% for vans
   Automate Task Assignment
- Designed and deployed an algorithm for solving the task assignment problem via an API endpoint, integrated into a system for periodic task assignment within the warehouse.
- Impact: Increased on-time dispatch by 16%

## System Design

#### Micro-services communication

- Designed and implemented a **gRPC-based communication system** across three services to transmit information at specific events, tested it in a QA environment, and oversaw its system-wide deployment.
- **Impact:** Decreased driver idle time by 7 minutes

### Spatial Database Model

- Developed a **spatial database model** which can store polygonal area and query with intersecting geolocation
- Impact: Enhanced vehicle utilization by restricting certain vehicle types in specific areas

## Re-Modeling Task Assignment system

- Designed a more efficient task assignment model, refactored existing models, redesigned the UI, and improved underlying logic.
- Impact: Increased picker's efficiency by 1.2x

#### **CONFERENCES AND TALKS**

## State of the Map Asia 2024

30 Nov-1 Dec, 2024

Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh

Invited to present a talk on the opportunities of OpenStreetMap and how to contribute to the community

#### How BUET Alumni Help Build Infrastructure of Bangladesh through Software

05 March, 2024

BUET, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Discussed my work, its impact on Bangladesh's infrastructure, and how it differs from a traditional software engineering role.

## NSysS 2023 - 10th International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security

21-23 December, 2023

BUET, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Presented our paper accepted in the conference alongside my co-author

# EAI MobiQuitous 2023 - 20th EAI International Conference on Mobile and Ubiquitous Systems: Computing, Networking and Services 14-17 November, 2023

RMIT University, Melbourne, Australia

Presented our research work at the time alongside my co-author

## EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES AND LEADERSHIP

### BUET CSE Fest AI Contest 15-23 July, 2022

Lead Organizer

Actively managed, set problem and judged the submissions of AI contest that had over 100 participants, hosted in codingame.com

#### ACHIEVEMENTS AND AWARDS

2022	$5^{th}/50$	Code Samurai Hackathon
2021		Hackerrank: Problem Solving (Intermediate)
2020		Codeforces Max Rating: Expert (1871)
2019	$8^{th}/86$	BUET CSE FEST IUPC
		DUET IUPC
2019	$13^{th}/59$	NSU Cybernauts National Programming Contest
		RUET IUPC
2019	$14^{th}/84$	IUT IUPC
2019	$18^{th}/109$	SUB IUPC
2019	$34^{th}/119$	SUST IUPC
2016	$2^{nd}/100$	Laboratorians Festival Math Olympiad
2015	$8^{th}/1000$	Regional Math Olympiad
2014	$2^{nd}/500$	National Astronomy & Astrophysics Olympiad

#### SELECTED PROJECTS

## Trapped (Game)

Unity Game Engine, C#

Developed a 2D action and puzzle platformer

Codingame: Steal The Flag

Java

Developed and hosted a game on codingame.com

## P5js-Raycasting

Javascript, HTML

Implemented raycasting using p5-js library for visualization

## xv6 Memory Management (OS)

Linux, C, bash, kernel programming

Enhanced the xv6 operating system by adding support for memory management.

## Simple C Compiler

C, YACC, Bison

Developed a C compiler capable of reading small C programs and generating corresponding machine code for execution.

## **CNN from Scratch**

Python

A simple implementation of a convolutional neural network using Python and NumPy, trained on the NumtaDB dataset to recognize Bengali digits.

## Chaldaal (Web App)

django/python, oracle/sql, HTML/CSS, JS

Created an online grocery shop similar to chaldal.com

## **Smart Construction Work System (Web App)**

Django, SQLite, HTML/CSS, JS

Developed a citywide smart construction management system

#### REFERENCES

#### Dr. Sadia Sharmin

Associate Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

Email: sadiasharmin@cse.buet.ac.bd,

sadia@teacher.cse.buet.ac.bd Contact: +880 1817 108555

## Dr. A. B. M. Alim Al Islam

Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

Email: alim\_razi@cse.buet.ac.bd Contact: +880 1817 533953

#### Dr. Mohammed Eunus Ali

Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

Email: eunus@cse.buet.ac.bd Contact: +880 2 9665612

### Dr. Jannatun Noor

Assistant Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

Brac University

Email: Jannatun.noor@bracu.ac.bd Contact: +880 1911 058877